Estonian, Latvian, Lithuanian Alliance Of Connecticut (ELLA) Records
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Estonian, Latvian, Lithuanian Alliance Of Connecticut (Ella) Records.
1938-1996.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Estonian, Latvian, Lithuanian Alliance Of Connecticut (ELLA).
1.75 linear feet.
MSS19970040
In 1987, the Estonian, Latvian, Lithuanian Alliance of Connecticut (ELLA) was formed to alert federal and state officials on issues concerning their respective countries. In particular, ELLA was formed to provide the media with accurate information on Baltic causes. Through these efforts, ELLA promotes a better understanding of the historic Baltic peoples as well as their contemporary problems.
History
Residents of the state of Connecticut of Estonian, Latvian, and Lithuanian descent have a natural interest in the lands of their heritage, collectively known as the Baltic countries. In 1987, the Estonian, Latvian, Lithuanian Alliance of Connecticut (ELLA) was formed to alert federal and state officials on issues concerning their respective countries. In particular, ELLA was formed to provide the media with accurate information on Baltic causes. Through these efforts, ELLA promotes a better understanding of the historic Baltic peoples as well as their contemporary problems.
From its inception, ELLA made Baltic independence its primary goal. Black Ribbon Day Commemorations and rallies in Hartford sharpened the general public's awareness of the Baltics' struggle. At the same time, the board of directors of ELLA began a serious lobbying effort in behalf of Baltic independence that centered on the Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact signed on 23 August 1939. Consequently, in 1991 when the “January Crisis” occurred and Soviet paratroopers cracked down on the independence movement, ELLA was ready to respond to Soviet disinformation, but, more importantly, able to give precise information about the bloody crackdown in Lithuania and Latvia. ELLA telegrammed the President and wrote members of Congress urging an immediate Soviet withdrawal.
For about a decade ELLA was a liaison and a lobbying organization to the thirty thousand Americans of Baltic descent living in Connecticut who maintain strong ties to their homeland. Of equal importance, ELLA has underscored Baltic events to all citizens who are interested in promoting democracy throughout the world.
ILVI JOE-CANNON
Ilvi Joe-Cannon, formerly of of Bolton, Connecticut, and in Tallinin, Estonia, as of 1997, donated the ELLA papers to the Dodd Research Center Archives & Special Collections in 1997. She was born in Viljandi, Estonia, but in 1944 fled to the West with her mother, brother, and two sisters, to avoid being deported to Siberia. In 1950 after having stayed in displaced persons camps in Germany, the family immigrated to the United States. In 1961, Ilvi Joe-Cannon received her B.A. from the University of Connecticut and in 1966 she received her M.A. from Indiana University.
Joe-Cannon, one of the founders of ELLA, later became chair of the organization. Continuing with work on Baltic causes, in 1994 she became the chair of the Baltic, Central, and East European Coalition (BCEEC), which is comprised of ELLA; the Polish-American Congress, the District of CT, Inc., the Hungarian Club, and the Ukrainian Congress Committee.
Scope and Content
The papers of the Estonian, Latvian, and Lithuanian Alliance of Connecticut consist of materials gathered by charter members of ELLA, in particular Ilvi-Joe Cannon, in an effort to document the history of the organization. The papers consist primarily of correspondence, newspaper clippings, facsimiles, photographs, and memorabilia. In addition, they include records of two other lobbying groups, which have similar objectives to ELLA's, the Joint Baltic American National Committee and the Baltic, Central, and East European Coalition. The papers also include records and correspondence from the Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe.
Arrangement
Series I: ELLA, ( 1986-1994 ) contains a statement of purpose, minutes of meetings, annual reports, fundraisers, and chronologically arranged lobbying files. The papers also contain letters from members of Congress, which include, Christopher Dodd, Joseph Lieberman, Bruce Morrison, Gary Franks, Barbara Kennelly, Christopher Shays, Alfonse D'Amato, Nancy Johnson, Rosa DeLauro, and Sam Gejdenson. Presidents Reagan, G.H.W. Bush, and Clinton also registered their support for Baltic independence. Cannon has included in the ELLA papers an extensive collection of newspaper clippings on Black Ribbon Day to recall the infamous 1939 Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact.
Series II: Other Organizations ( 1987-1996 )consists of chronologically arranged reports from the Joint Baltic American National Committee, the Baltic, Central, and East European Coalition of Connecticut, and the U.S. Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe.
Series III: Related Papers ( 1938-1996 )includes materials on privatization in Estonia, Estonian culture, personal testimonies, books, White House invitations, an ELLA survey, USID News, ELLA related concerns, and correspondence. The papers are arranged alphabetically by subject. Included in the ELLA papers is Joe-Cannon's personal narrative, A Mighty Hand: The Story of an Estonian Family.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to Connecticut's ethnic communities. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Estonian, Latvian, Lithuanian Alliance of Connecticut—History.; Baltic States—History.; Baltic States—Foreign relations—United States.; Baltic States—Politics and government.; Connecticut—Baltic immigrants.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Personal Papers.; Publications.; Photographs.; Administrative Records.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Ilvi Joe-Cannon of Bolton, Connecticut, donated the ELLA Records in 1996.
Detailed Description
- Series I: ELLA, 1986-1994
  - Statement of Purpose, 1987 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - First meeting and first annual report, 1987 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - ELLA representatives, 1987-1988 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - ELLA minutes, 1987-1994 (Box 1:, Folder 4-6)
  - Annual report, 1988-1989 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Fundraisers, 1988-1994 (Box 1:, Folder 8-11)
  - “Sister Cities” dispute, 1986-1990 (Box 1:, Folder 12-14)
  - Political correspondence, 1987-1994 (Box 2:, Folder 15-22)
  - ELLA survey, 1988 (Box 2:, Folder 23)
  - Lobbying Gorbachev, 1987-1991 (Box 2:, Folder 24)
  - Legal representation, 1988 (Box 2:, Folder 25)
  - Baltic Freedom Day correspondence, 1988 (Box 2:, Folder 26)
  - Black Ribbon Day, 1989 (Box 2:, Folder 27)
  - Actions and correspondence: “January Crisis”, 1991 (Box 2:, Folder 28)
  - Baltic Thanksgiving, 1991 (Box 2:, Folder 29)
  - Facsimiles, 1990-1991 (Box 2:, Folder 30)
- Series II: Other Organizations, 1987-1996
  - Joint Baltic American National Committee, 1989-1995 (Box 3:, Folder 31)
  - Baltic, Central, And East European Coalition
    - Minutes and notes, 1995-1996 (Box 3:, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence, 1995-1996 (Box 3:, Folder 33)
    - Initiatives, 1994-1996 (Box 3:, Folder 34)
  - Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe, 1988-1994 (Box 3:, Folder 35-38)
  - Federal/state legislators, 1988-1995 (Box 3:, Folder 39)
  - Baltic move for independence, 1987-1989 (Box 3:, Folder 40)
  - Press coverage: Baltic Independence, 1988-1989 (Box 3:, Folder 41)
  - Baltic Freedom Day: Congressional actions, 1989 (Box 3:, Folder 42)
  - Red Army withdrawal, 1992-1993 (Box 3:, Folder 43)
  - Related Baltic interests, 1981-1991 (Box 3:, Folder 44)
  - U.S. Baltic aid, 1991-1994 (Box 3:, Folder 45)
- Series III: Related Papers, 1938-1996
  - Americares, 1991-1992 (Box 4:, Folder 46)
  - ELLA invitations, 1993-1996 (Box 4:, Folder 47)
  - Estonian church, 1953-1994 (Box 4:, Folder 48)
  - Estonian culture, 1989-1995 (Box 4:, Folder 49)
  - Estonian cultural activities, 1984-1995 (Box 4:, Folder 50)
  - Estonian Veterans League, 1952-1992 (Box 4:, Folder 51)
  - Historic documents, 1938-1979 (Box 4:, Folder 52)
  - Joe-Cannon, Ilvi, A Mighty Hand, 1996 (Box 4:, Folder 53)
  - Official proclamations, 1987-1990 (Box 4:, Folder 54)
  - Personal testimonies, 1982-1988 (Box 4:, Folder 55)
  - Privatization (Estonia), 1993 (Box 4:, Folder 56)
  - Related concerns, 1989-1996 (Box 4:, Folder 57)
  - Rutas, U., Dear God I Want to Live, 1982 (Box 4:, Folder 58)
  - Skema, Antanas, The Awakening, 1988 (Box 4:, Folder 59)
  - USID news releases, 1989-1994 (Box 4:, Folder 60)